software engineering radio episode 71
survey results
[Music]
hello listeners here is Marcus from se
radio I wanted to give you a little
heads-up about the survey we've recently
done so we have reached 1,000
participants that's a significant number
that makes the results statistically
relevant or significant or whatever it's
officially called so thank you all for
participating in the survey for those
who did participate and well maybe next
time for the others I wanted to give you
some information about the results
I will also reply to some of the
suggestions and criticisms that we
received through the survey so let's
briefly step through the questions the
first question was about the age and we
have the range between 20 and 30 and
between 30 and 40 we have roughly 40%
we have 15% between 40 and 50 and then
we have some really old and some really
young so as expected the average is
around between 20 and 40 the job role is
70% developers we have 25% team leads we
have that's interesting with 15%
research people and also 15% students
35% calls themselves an architect and
remember you could select several of
these so the sum is not 100% what is
interesting is the size of the
organization you are in 30% are in
organizations with more than 1,000
people and then we have another major
subgroup with 20% between 100 100,000 we
have 10% freelancers and 4% very small
companies 73% of you work in software
consulting or software development and
another 20% in telecom or communications
with 7% healthcare and another 7% in
defense and 5% aerospace and 6%
automotive in academia 88% of the people
were
in computer science and around 5% in
electrical engineering and Sciences but
of course only like 10% of view of the
overall or 15 percent of the overall
audience are academics so with regards
to the kinds of applications you develop
and the prize 55% web 20% tool
developers that's interesting so we'll
have to cover tool development issues a
little bit more we have 20% embedded
that is not enough I want more embedded
and technical people in the audience and
that's also why we will focus on
embedded stuff a little bit more in the
coming episodes we have 10% mobile and
30% rich client which also leads me to
maybe an emphasis we should have the
future and talk about rich client and
GUI and client development in general
what is interesting to see and I'm
really happy about that is that 55% of
you have between 5 and 20 years of
experience 10% have more than 20 years
our goal is to be a podcast for
professional developers for experienced
developers and looking at that
statistics here seems that we reach this
goal well at least to some extent 40% of
you have a master's degree another 40% a
Bachelor and we have 7% PhD and we have
half a percent professors by the way if
you didn't see that question when you
replied to the survey what I actually
while while looking at the results from
the survey from the first couple of
responses we came up with additional
questions so we relatively quickly added
another bunch of questions and one of
them was the degree you'll see more of
that later so how long have you listened
to as you radio we have a 15% have
listened from the beginning in January
2006 and the majority started during
2007 40 % listen only to some
results not to all of them there are
about 30% who listen to all of them
it's a little bit unfortunate I would
really love to hear that people listen
to all episodes because the goal of SU
radio is to cover topics that are maybe
not necessarily your prime concern when
developing or when working in your
everyday job so I would really encourage
you to listen to other episodes that do
not necessarily fit directly your your
developer your professional profile most
people download all episodes they'll
download well sorry
most people listen to all the episodes
they download only 10% only download
things and then decide that's of course
interesting to us because if we collect
download numbers and we don't know how
many people listen to what they download
we can't cancel anything about the
listenership yeah and the other question
of course was how how do you share the
downloaded mp3 file and 80% don't share
it with any other people but it's
interesting to see that about 15% share
it with one or two other people and
there are even people who share it with
more than five others so that's that
that of course increases our audience
reach compared to the download numbers
the length of the episodes is something
I want to address briefly so the
majority about 60% to say that between
35 and 50 minutes is it about right and
that's probably also the majority of our
episodes then with the typical length so
the 20 to 35 minute things are really
short I mean within 20 minutes you
cannot really explain a topic we
probably tend to have longer episodes
although I agree that 50 to 70 minutes
is quite a bit long so I think it's
gonna be it's going to continue to be
between 40 and maybe 60 minutes and we
also received the feedback quite a
couple of times that well that's too
long I don't have such a long commute
and I can't listen to that in one in one
go but well I mean there is the pause
button right so I mean just stop
and and continue at another time I'll do
that all the time when I listen to other
podcasts oh I don't think that's
necessarily a problem although I agree I
mean there is the space show podcast for
example where episodes often or two
hours and that's too long so well I
think the majority of people are between
35 and 50 minutes and that's also I
think my sweet spot with regards to the
length so that fits well how did you
learn about SU radio most people found
it while googling well obviously 35% and
then of course you have word of mouth
only 25% of the people found su radio by
following a link from another webpage
and that is something I really I'm not
yet satisfied with we need a bigger
community and I don't really know how to
build that but what I really would like
to ask you as an audience is to put
links to su radio on on your website I
mean that's a very easy way or or blog
about us say a couple of nice words
publicly so people people fine doesn't
know about us that would really help
it's free for you it's not much work and
it helps us a great deal
so um we'd be happy if you helped us
there a little bit more the following
two questions have been added also later
in the game and they're concerned
sponsoring and how we could make some
money and just to Pleakley be clear
about that as your radio is
non-commercial and we're not planning to
become rich from doing as your radio but
I mean for example we are currently
working on a new website you can't get
that for free or another thing is like
if we wanted to buy decent microphones
to address the audio quality topic that
many people complained about it's not
free so we would like to have a couple
of thousand euros as a team per year so
we can do these kinds of things so we
had two questions one was how would you
react if we had sponsoring or
advertising in the podcast and five
percent said that they would not listen
to se radio if there was any advertising
well I think that's a quite a bit
intolerant I mean most if not all other
podcasts do have some kind of
sponsorship II
by explicit advertisements in the show
or simply by allowing the people to work
on some of the podcast issues during
their work time but 50% of the people
said that advertising would be okay if
it was for a good company and if it
wouldn't be too much well and that's
kind of the the thing they had in mind
another forty five percent said I don't
care do whatever you want to keep the
podcast going here is what I had in mind
for example if we could find a company
that does really interesting work for it
for example in the embedded space so for
example in the beginning of the podcast
we would say well this podcast is
supported by XYZ company and then at the
end we would have one minute of specific
content that they recalled and they that
would clearly be distinguishable by some
kind of background music or something
well they say you know well we've
recently done our first project with
embedded Linux and it was really great
and here is some of the problems some of
the solutions and if you want to learn
more go to our website we have a white
paper that describes it so that is
clearly advertising because it
advertises what a specific company did
but it's also to some extent a little
bit of value add for you because people
who are interested in that stuff might
want to look at the paper so that's an
idea I had and of course there would be
different content in each episode and we
would clearly mark it as being
advertising another idea that I had was
to talk to book publishers and I gave
give them the chance in the same way as
I explained before to spend one minute
or so per episode briefly introducing
and you book or something so that's what
we're thinking about and I'll keep you
posted of what we were doing there it
will not be in the middle of the show it
will not be in the Leo Laporte way where
the person who does the the content of
the episode starts talking about
something and you know disguising the
advertising and more or less so it will
be explicit will be at the end and it
will be limited so that's what we're
thinking about and well let's see there
was a related question that we asked
about donations because I mean if we can
get the money from you
the audience instead of
having a sponsor then that would also
work and sixty-five percent said that
they would not be willing to donate
twenty percent would be willing to
donate one or two dollars per month ten
percent said they would be willing to
donate two to five dollars per month and
there would be people five percent no
well five present who would donate more
than five dollars per month if people
would actually really do donate then we
would get enough money to cover the cost
so here is what I would propose we are
not going to look for advertising in the
next three months so if you guys really
start donating the amount of money you
have set that you would be willing to
donate just do it and we'll see how that
goes
currently I mean you know since the
podcast has been running two years ago
we have received overall maybe a hundred
or 150 dollars in donation so I if you
would really do donate the amount that
you specified here then our problem
would be solved and we wouldn't need to
do any any advertisement so I would
really like to ask you to start donating
for let's say for the next three months
and and we'll see how this turns out
I'll keep you posted
I will be open about that and and if
that works out we won't do any
sponsoring okay back to the results of
the survey 75% like the interviews with
important folks but another 70% like the
tutorial episodes from within the team
60% like episodes with regular people
who have interesting stuff to say so
there is no strong peak so I think we'll
keep the mix as it is 85% like
conceptual stuff in overviews 55%
research oriented stuff and 60%
down-to-earth how to's I will have to
say something about that I'm not sure
that covering detailed low-level things
is is a good thing for a podcast to do
because we're only audio at least in my
experience it is easier and more
feasible to communicate at the overviews
and the
more conceptual stuff as opposed to
low-level stuff because if you're
low-level you get to the point where you
have to write code or look at diagrams
and stuff so we will probably focus on
the conceptual stuff and oh you kind of
thing and from time to time also have
lower-level detailed more detailed stuff
the question about the following aspects
of software engineering 65% languages
81% prefer architecture stuff maybe we
should call ourself the architecture
caste process issues are 44% so that
also hits the distribution we had in the
past that we mostly look at
architectural stuff languages and the
process stuff is important but not quite
as important as the technical stuff and
85% really like 80 sorry 80% really like
concurrency patterns in these kinds of
things 60% of you listen to Java posi
30% this week in tech security now
another 20% and 30% listen to the Google
developer podcast 50% look at Slashdot
regularly the server-side is another 43%
in foq 30%
Joel on software 40% so that's kind of
the kind of community we're in only
about 10 or 15% of the people go to
conferences regularly and from those 15%
30% could have been or go - oops la
Jacks 30% or P 42 percent so that's the
the results from the numbers I have also
a couple of more specific points that
have been that you replied to us in the
freeform stuff so let me say something
about that one person gave us the
feedback that they really liked our mix
from enterprise to embedded and as I
said before we'll really continue to do
that we want to really cover all aspects
of software engineering and not be the
enterprise caste there was also the
feedback that there is too much
enterprise stuff and I agree to that we
had well it's probably the biggest
community so that's why we talk to
Father for quite a bit but we will focus
on other topics in the future I mean I
talked about the embedded stuff we will
look at game development a bit we will
look at artificial intelligence a little
bit and of course the language thing so
we have quite a broad spectrum in the
future and I think the enterprise stuff
will certainly not become more it
probably will become less of a focus one
guy criticized that sometimes the
interviewer can get too much in the way
of the speaker trying to make his own
points and demonstrating his knowledge
sure I mean you know the the people who
do the interviews are not journalists in
that sense they are in the community
themselves they do have their own
opinions they do have their own messages
and they do have experience usually and
also since this is a non-commercial
things to some extent the people dinner
viewers also want to show that they know
what they're talking about so I think
that's probably going to continue I mean
sure if we interview person X then it's
not about the interviewer but I'm sure
we can't completely remove that the
interviewers are also to some extent
part of the episodes somebody mentioned
that although he understands that we do
this stuff for free and in our spare
time they would like to hear episodes
more frequently well same thing I mean
we we're not able to produce more they
just there is not more time if and I'm
really putting a big question mark here
if you would donate so much money that
we could actually consider this podcast
as part of our well professional work
where we paid for then we will certainly
produce more episodes of course there is
also drawbacks I mean if we did this
more or less commercially then of course
many people wouldn't necessarily be
willing to talk to us because they're
not necessarily willing to help us make
money so well I think the ten-day thing
is probably quite reasonable we also do
this like a clockwork you can be sure
you get your new episodes every 10 days
so I think that's probably the way it's
going to stay people said less Java so
actually I am personally very interested
in not making this a Java podcast
because there
Java and we don't want to be
competitors in that space nonetheless
most of the people I work with because
of my personal background do have a Java
background in some sense the point is
that if I come up with an example and
don't think much about it it'll always
be Java so while we try not to become a
Java cast the kind of between the lines
Java and Ness will probably probably
remain for the foreseeable future there
is also a recommendation of other
formats for example panel discussions
panel discussions are not that easy and
there are well the reason is that you
have to coordinate four or five people
and find a time slot there everybody has
time and that's almost impossible I mean
we all have regular lives the
interviewees interviewees have regular
lives and the only way to get two panels
is to basically record them when people
meet personally at a conference or to
recall an existing panel that has been
set up somewhere else but we don't want
to do this we do not want to rebroadcast
stuff that has been recorded on
conferences or something because we want
to produce original content so I really
like the panel discussion format but I'm
a little bit skeptical about organizing
it for the podcast again because of the
finding a common timeslot thing somebody
asked us to produce a bunch of episodes
in German and we're certainly not going
to do this because we have didn't
mention that before we have about thirty
thirty percent of our listeners speak
German and the rest is spread all over
the world and does not speak German so
we're not going to alienate seventy
percent this is going to stay an
international podcast and if you are not
able to to listen to the English we
speak which sometimes might not be
perfect because we're mostly not native
speakers then I apologize for that but
it's it's not going to change we
shouldn't do so many summaries we should
do we should go down to the real
detailed gritty nitty gritty stuff and
again well it's it's it's a problem of
communicating details or on an audio
only so I think while I accept the
criticism
I don't know how to how to actually
implement it specifically the guy said
that the embedded systems intro has very
little or useful content that's true it
was explicitly intended as an overview
and we'll have many more detailed
episodes coming up in the next twenty or
something so then there is the the
never-ending topic about audio quality I
really don't know I mean in the
beginning we had problems I agree and
also today we sometimes have the problem
that we have to recall in a venue where
it's not perfectly quiet or the
interviewee is only willing to do it
over regular telephone lines and then of
course you have the telephone sound but
you know it's not professional we don't
have a studio we recall that all over
the world in places all over the world
and it's very hard to improve it when we
do interviews remotely what we try to do
is to make everybody the interviewer and
the interviewee record their own track
locally and then merge those tracks so
we do not record via Skype we only
coordinate via Skype
so if we have episodes done within the
team that works but if if we interview
somebody some like you know like big
name we can't necessarily tell them that
they have to set up audacity and record
locally they're just not gonna do this
so you will have to be a little bit
tolerant with regards to the audio
quality and I think generally we are
pretty good I mean at least if you look
at the more recent episodes yes we had
trouble in the beginning but the more
recent episodes are well the next one
might be a little bit of a problem but
that's a special case in general I think
it's fairly ok people suggested for us
to create video casts and that's
something that you won't see from se
radio in the foreseeable future for
several reasons first of all it's simply
way more work you need more equipment
the editing is more complicated and
therefore we won't do this the other
thing is that I've seen several video
casts on software where people the
interviewer and the interviewee sit
around the table
and talk well I don't need to see those
guys okay I there's no point in making
this a videocast if you don't show
people standing in front of a flip chart
or showing slides or something
we won't produce video casts and if you
want video you have to go somewhere else
exactly a message that's not going to
change in the foreseeable future then
there is this thing where got this
feedback a couple of times at Marcus
that's probably me gets a bit
overexcited about MDA and tends to see
everything in this context well I think
I have a pretty broad spectrum on on
software development but true I mean my
focus is modeling model driven product
lines architecture these kinds of stuff
and well I mean to some extent the
podcast is also my platform and of
course that's also true for all the
other people involved in the team and as
I said before they they do want to also
make their positions known and we are
not necessarily the completely oblivious
journalists that just asks questions so
I think you have to live with that I
mean it's not going to it I think it's
not that bad but well that's just the
way it is somebody said that some of our
interviewees are totally disorganized
can't present can't talk well that might
certainly happen from time to time you
know but the problem is we cannot record
an interview with somebody and then say
you know you were not structured enough
and then throw it away I mean that would
just frustrate people that people will
talk about that and will have a tough
time finding additional interviewees so
yeah from time to time there might be an
episode that's not that perfect in that
sense okay I mean either live with it or
don't listen press the stop button and
download the next one there is one thing
that was mentioned did you consider an S
II radio conference and actually I
thought about that what I would like to
do would be some kind of open space kind
of thing where we do like discussions
and workshops we don't we didn't do
anything concrete there yet we would
also have to do this in partnership with
some kind of organization that helps us
organize that stuff I'm not sure it's a
good thing I mean there is a whole bunch
of conferences already you can argue
that there are already too many
conferences and not every media has to
have a magazine a podcast a videocast
and a conference I mean we're a podcast
we have exclusive podcast content and I
tend to think that that should be the
way it should stay well let me know send
us an email if you would like to come to
such as your radio conference and how
you would like it to be and we can think
about it
but it's certainly not the primary focus
there was one guy who said that quality
of the content is good topics chosen our
good sound quality and presentation is
really bad hmm
I don't know if you who wrote that
listen now well if you could give us a
little bit more specific feedback that
would be helpful I'm not sure I can
react to this kind of general statement
and the last thing I want to mention is
actually acquired a quite funny comment
it said just keep it technical and keep
all the human touch seriously unless
you're as good as Leo Laporte just focus
on the facts yeah I think that's that's
a nice word towards the end he'll
probably do that because yeah sure I
mean if you look at listen to Leo
I mean he's it's fascinating how he can
how he can do this I mean there's not
nothing on in the podcast world that
that's on par with him I think from a
radio voice and communications
perspective so let's very briefly look
at some of the topics you suggested of
course we will not do more Java we will
do less Java
I'm also sensitive to the fact that we
already did a lot of MDS D modeling DSL
stuff so that'll not increase but from
time to time you know it's my speciality
from time to time that will be something
we will look at game development in the
future we will have a focus on embedded
stuff and also we did not forget the
testing aspect we the last episode the
latest episode that you've just heard
was with Jeremy sorrows on on testing
and will we have another couple of
testing things in the pipeline
many of you suggested specific people to
talk to and thanks for the suggestions
we'll look at them
many people suggested Martin Fowler and
actually Todd talked to him recently and
at some point he'll be willing to do
something so that'll happen at some
point we also will look at XML of course
that's something we didn't look at yet
that will come security is something
well that we'll cover to some extent but
there is security now which is quite a
good security podcast we're not going to
try to replicate that although I
understand that there is a security
aspect that is more related to
development and that's not covered very
much in security now Microsoft
specificness will actually have episodes
with Microsoft people coming up we
already had Microsoft people for example
Drago's modelesque ooh we're probably
not going to talk too much about
Microsoft specific technologies because
at least in the current structure of the
team there are many people who have a
good you know understanding of that and
can can can come up with really good
questions and stuff somebody suggested
trust of charnetski as well actually
several people suggested closed off as
somebody we should interview and
actually I did that recently so there
will be an at Janet's key interview at
some point I don't know yet when it's
going to be broadcast so um thank you
very much for for all the suggestions
450 people expressed what they wanted to
hear it's a huge amount of stuff and of
course as you can imagine more or less
every topic has been suggested some
topics have been brought to my mind that
I offer to my attention that I didn't
consider before so thank you very much
we have a long time to go as your radio
is not going to stop in a year it's it's
a long time and ever and we will cover
probably most of the topics you
suggested at some point or another but
of course it's very hard to cover
everything in the next five episodes so
that's all I wanted to say thank you
very much for the survey and to get back
to this sponsoring thing which is maybe
the topic that's most directly relevant
or in the short term please just go
ahead and start the
and we'll see how this goes and if if
there is a significant amount of money
coming in for example let's say I don't
know $200 per month or 300 which
according to the survey should be no
problem then that'll be it we will not
do any sponsoring we don't want to make
money we just want to be able to cover
our cost so start donating and we'll see
how it goes if you have any additional
suggestions of course as usual send mail
to the team at se
- radio net and well keep the feedback
going and if you want to do as a favor
in addition or instead of donating just
spread the word talk about SU radio on
forums you know I can't like talk nicely
about the podcast you know you have to
do this so mention has your radio on
discussion groups mention us to your
colleagues put links and logos off on
your webpage and just spread the word
and by the way I did not forget that we
promised books they are actually here on
my desk I will have to go to the US now
for two weeks
oops la and some other stuff so when I
returned to Germany when I'm back home
we will send around the books and then
find the winners I don't want to
announce people on the air I mean you
didn't kind of agree to be announced
over the air maybe you'll receive a book
maybe you won't we have six or seven
books to to send away so you'll hear
from us if you are the lucky winner
thank you very much thanks for taking
part in the survey
it helps us quite a bit understanding
what the audience is all about and many
of the very positive comments you gave
us also keeps us going Thanks
and well talk to you in some future
episode - fine
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details